Register of the Lewis A. Maverick papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Lewis A. Maverick papers
1914-1940
XX245
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes (2.0 linear feet)
The Lewis A. Maverick papers consist of correspondence, photographs, essays, reports, memoranda, diaries, newspaper clippings, and other documents related to the Henry Ford Peace Expedition (1915), the Neutral Conference for Continuous Mediation and International Committee for Immediate Mediation (1916), and various other peace organizations around the world and in the United States.
Maverick, Lewis A.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1891 Born in Texas to George Madison Maverick and Mary Vance Maverick
1915 Joined the Henry Ford Peace Expedition
1946-1959 Taught at Southern Illinois University Carbondale
1973 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, photographs, essays, reports, memoranda, diaries, newspaper clippings, and other documents related to the Henry Ford Peace Expedition (1915), the Neutral Conference for Continuous Mediation and International Committee for Immediate Mediation (1916), and various other peace organizations around the world and in the United States.
Henry Ford Peace Expedition.; Pacifism.; Peace.; United States--Neutrality.; World War, 1914-1918--Peace.
- Biographical File, 1915-1917 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Personal effects belonging to Lewis A. Maverick. Includes membership cards, pins, business cards (not Maverick's), donation cards, and other items.
- Speeches and Writings, 1915-1934
  - Essays and reports, 1915-1934 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    Formal essays and reports written and/or edited by Lewis A. Maverick. Topics include the Henry Ford Peace Expedition and other issues concerning world peace.
  - Notes, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    Handwritten notes made by Lewis A. Maverick on various subjects concerning his personal and business affairs, including drafts of essays and statements.
  - Diary, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    Loose-leaf diary entries kept by Lewis A. Maverick over the course of the Henry Ford Peace Expedition.
- Correspondence, 1915-1940 (Box-folder 1: 5-6)
  Correspondence received and sent by Lewis A. Maverick.
- Rosika Schwimmer, 1915-1941
  - Correspondence, 1915-1941 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    Correspondence received and sent by Rosika Schwimmer.
  - Miscellaneous documents, 1915-1940 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    Reports, newspaper clippings, flyers, and other documents concerning Rosika Schwimmer, including information on a campaign to gain Schwimmer the World Peace Prize.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  Other correspondence not received or sent by Lewis A. Maverick or Rosika Schwimmer.
- Subject Files, 1915-1918
  - Olaf Forchhammer, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    Olaf Forchhammer,Cophenhagen's city engineer from 1936-1951, was a pacifist and board member of the Danish Peace Society.
  - Henry Ford Peace Expedition, 1915-1916
    Print media concerning theories about peace, Henry Ford Peace Expedition logistics, and other issues relevant to the Expedition, which was aimed at promoting peace in Europe during World War I and brokering an agreement between the belligerent countries to put an end to the fighting.
    - Biographical monographs, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 2: 3)
      Books on the members of the Expedition.
    - Biographies and lists, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      Biographical information on the members of the Expedition.
    - Bulletins and circulars, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 2: 5-6)
    - Menus, programs, and trip logistics, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - Photographs, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 2: 8)
      One album page of photographs related to the Expedition.
      See also: Box 5.
    - Documents, reports, and essays, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - Financial records, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 2: 10)
      Expense reports, calculations, fund request forms, and other material relating to Expedition expenditures.
  - Neutral Conference for Continuous Mediation, 1916
    - Peace plans, reports, documents, and speeches (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
  - Seventh Scandinavian Student Meeting, 1916 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Foreign Delegations Reports, 1916 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - People's Council of America, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - American Union Against Militarism, 1917 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Emergency Peace Federation, undated (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - International Peace Movements, circa 1917 (Box-folder 3: 8)
- Photographs, circa 1915-1916 (Box 5)
  Five photo albums of photographs, mainly related to the Henry Ford Peace Expedition and its members and events. Also includes an album containing photo negatives and three separate envelopes containing more negatives and other loose photographs. Notes made by Lewis A. Maverick can be found inside the albums and envelopes.
  See also: Box 2, Folder 8.
- Printed Matter, 1915-1934
  Consists of pamphlets, flyers, books, and booklets.
  - Pamphlets, flyers, books, and booklets, 1915-1934 (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
  - Newspapers and clippings, 1915-1940
    Full newspapers, articles, clippings, magazines, and other print publications.
    - 1915, undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - 1916 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - 1917 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - 1918-1940 (Box-folder 4: 4)